Guide to the Group Research, Inc. Records,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Group Research, Inc. Records,
1955-1996
Group Research, Inc.
215 linear ft. (512 document boxes; 1 map case; 1 flat box ).
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library. New York, NY.
5010936
History
Wesley McCune founded Group Research Inc. in 1962 after a successful career as a journalist for such magazines as "Newsweek", "Time", "Life", and "Changing Times". In addition, McCune worked as well as a staff member of several government agencies and government-related organizations. Based in Washington DC until ceasing operations in the mid-1990s Group Research Inc. collected materials that focus on the right-wing and span four decades. The resulting Group Research archive includes information about and by right-wing organizations and a ctivists in the form of publications correspondence pamphlets reports newspaper "Congressional Record" and magazine clippings and other ephemera. The collection is thoroughly cross-referenced and contains the Group Research Directory which, dating mostly from the 1960s, provides brief histories of prominent people organizations and publications associated with the right wing. McCune and his small staff also published an initially bi-monthly but in later years monthly newsletter Group Research Report which kept its subscribers abreast of the latest views and actions of right-wingers.
Scope and Content
McCune and his staff catalogued the collection to operate as a fully accessible library, and their organization, including their folder labels, has been maintained as much as possible. Most of the materials are arranged alphabetically by topic (rather than, for example, chronologically) and have been divided into three separate series. Four other series contain volumes of Group Research Report, larger printed works, audio-visual materials, and the Group Research Directory.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into 16 series:
Series I: Topical, 1955-1996
Series II: Topical, 1955-1996
Series III: States, 1955-1996
Series IV: Group Research Report, 1962-1996
Series V: Printed Materials, 1960-1985
Series VI: Audio/Visual
Series VII: Group Research Directory
Series VIII: Card Files
Series IX: Publications
Series X: Correspondence
Series XI: Manuscripts
Series XII: 1996 CPAC
Series XIII: Clippings
Series XIV: Bumper Stickers
Series XV: Audio/Visual Material
Series XVI: Manuscript Files on Audio/Visual Material
Subjects
John Birch Society.; Group Research, Inc.; Group Research Collection (Columbia University Libraries)--NNC.; Christian conservatism.; Conservatism--United States.; Pressure groups.; Political culture.; Political parties.; Political movements--United States.; Radicalism--United States.; Religious right.; Republicanism.; Right and left (Political science); Right-wing extremists--United States.
Access Restrictions
This collection has no restrictions.
The following boxes are located off-site: 1-506; 509-512. You will need to request this material from the Rare Book and Manuscript Library at least twenty-four (24) hours in advance to use the collection in the Rare Book and Manuscript Library reading room.
Acquisition
[source of acquisition] Purchase, 1996
- Series I: Topical Files
  - Abortion (Box 1)
    [See Series 2 -- Abortion.]
  - Abraham Lincoln National Republican Club (Box 1)
  - Abshire, David (Box 1)
  - Accuracy in Media, 1991 (Box 1)
  - Accuracy In Media, 1986- (Box 1)
  - Accuracy In Media, 1980- (Box 1)
  - Accuracy In Media, 1974- (Box 1)
  - Accuracy In Media (Box 2)
  - Ad Hoc Committees (Box 2)
    [See also Series 2 -- Ad Hoc Committees.]
  - Adamson, Lee J. (Box 2)
  - Advance Magazine (Box 2)
  - Advertising (Box 2)
  - Afghanistan (Box 2)
  - Africa (Box 2)
  - African-American Institute (Box 2)
  - AFL-CIO (Box 2)
    [See also Series 2 -- American Federation of Labor and the Group Research directory under Special Reports -- Voting Records and Indexes.]
  - Agnew, Spiro (Box 2)
  - Agnew, Spiro T. (Gov.), MD (Box 2)
  - Air America, Inc. (Box 2)
  - Air Force Association (Box 2)
  - Alabama State Sovereignty Commission (Box 2)
    [See also Series 3 -- Alabama.]
  - Alamo Cult (Box 2)
  - Alert America Committee, The (Box 2)
  - Alert Americans Association (Box 2)
  - Alexander, Holmes (Box 3)
  - Alexander, Lamar (Box 3)
  - Alfalfa Club (Box 3)
  - Alger, Bruce (Rep.), R-TX (Box 3)
  - All-America Protectorate, Inc. St. Louis, MO (Box 3)
  - All American Conference to Combat Communism (Box 3)
  - Allegheny County League of Women Voters (Box 3)
  - Allegheny Foundation (Box 3)
  - Allen-Bradley Co. (Box 3)
  - Allen, Gary (Box 3)
  - Allen, George (Box 3)
  - Allen, Marilyn R. (Box 3)
  - Allen, Richard V. (Box 3)
  - Allen, Robert S. (Box 3)
  - Allen, Steve (Box 3)
  - Alliance, Inc. (Box 3)
  - Almond, Edward M. (Lt.Gen.), AL (Box 3)
    [See also the Group Research directory under Edward M. Almond.]
  - Alternative Educational Foundation (Box 4)
  - Ambassador College, Pasadena, CA (Box 4)
    [See also "The Plain Truth."]
  - America First Party (Box 4)
  - America, Wake Up Committee (Box 4)
  - American Academy of Achievement (Box 4)
  - American Academy of Public Affairs of Los Angeles, Los Angeles, CA (Box 4)
  - American Action (Box 4)
  - "American Adviser, The ", Sapulpa, OK (Box 4)
    [Owner/Editor, Glenn O. Young See also Glenn O. Young, New National Printing and Publishing Company, and the Group Research directory under "American Adviser, The."]
  - African-American Affairs Association, Inc. (Box 4)
  - American Afro-Asian Educational Exchange, Inc. Financial (Box 4)
  - American Afro-Asian Educational Exchange, Inc. (Box 5)
    [See also American-Asian Educational Exchange, Inc.]
  - American Agricultural Movement (AAM) (Box 5)
  - American-Asian Educational Exchange, Inc. (Box 5)
    [See also American Afro-Asian Educational Exchange, Inc.]
  - American Association for Justice, Inc. (Box 5)
  - American Association of Christian Schools (Box 5)
  - American Association of Retired Persons (AARP) (Box 5)
  - American Bar Association (ABA) (Box 5)
  - American Business Conference (Box 5)
  - American Capsule News (Box 5)
  - American Cause (Box 5)
  - American Challenge (Box 6)
  - American-Chillian Council (Box 6)
  - American China Policy Association (Box 6)
  - American Christian Education Associates (Box 6)
  - American Christian Heritage Association (Box 6)
  - American Civil Liberties Union (ACLU) (Box 6)
  - American Coalition for Traditional Values (Box 6)
  - American Coalition of Patriotic Societies "Report to America", Washignton, DC (Box 6)
    [See also the Group Research directory under American Coalition of Patriotic Societies.]
  - American Coalition of Patriotic Societies (Box 6)
  - American College, Milwaukee, WI (Box 6)
    [See also Gordon V. Drake.]
  - American College of Emergency Physicians, East Lansing, MI (Box 6)
  - American Colonization Society (Box 6)
  - American Committee for Aid to Katanga Freedom Fighters, New York, NY (Box 6)
    [See also Katanga and the Group Research directory under American Committee for Aid to Katanga Freedom Fighters.]
  - American Committee to Free Cuba, Inc. Arcadia, CA (Box 6)
    [See also the Group Research directory under American Committee to Free Cuba, Inc.]
  - American Conservative Party in Missouri, MO (Box 6)
  - American Conservative Union Miscellaneous Publications, Washington, DC (Box 6)
    [See also the Group Research directory under American Conservative Union.]
  - American Conservative Union, Washington, DC, 1989- (Box 7)
  - American Conservative Union, Washington, DC, 1982- (Box 7)
  - American Conservative Union, Washington, DC, 1980- (Box 7)
  - American Conservative Union, Washington, DC, 1979- (Box 7)
  - American Conservative Union, Washington, DC, 1978- (Box 8)
  - American Conservative Union, Washington, DC, 1976- (Box 8)
  - American Conservative Union, Washington, DC, 1974-5 (Box 8)
  - American Conservative Union, Washington, DC, 1971-3 (Box 8)
  - American Conservative Union, Washington, DC, 1969-70 (Box 9)
  - American Conservative Union, Washington, DC, 1965-8 (Box 9)
  - American Conservative Union Financial, Washington, DC (Box 9)
  - American Constitution Party (Box 9)
  - American Constitutional Defense Council, Inc. (Box 9)
  - American Council for Coordinated Action (Box 9)
  - American Council for Free Asia (Box 9)
  - American Council for Judaism, The (Box 9)
  - American Council for World Freedom (Box 9)
  - American Council of Christian Laymen Kaub, Philip P. (Box 9)
  - American Council of Young Political Leaders (Box 10)
  - American Council on Science and Health (Box 10)
  - American Defense Institute (Box 10)
  - American Defense Lobby (Box 10)
  - American Economic Foundation (AEF) General, New York, NY and Cleveland, OH, 1972- (Box 10)
    [See also the Group Research directory under American Economic Foundation (AEF).]
  - American Economic Foundation (AEF) Financial, New York, NY and Cleveland, OH (Box 10)
  - American Economic Foundation (AEF) Pamphlets, speeches, etc., New York, NY and Cleveland, OH (Box 10)
  - American Economic Foundation (AEF) General, New York, NY and Cleveland, OH (Box 10)
  - American Economic Foundation (AEF) Hall of Free Enterprise, New York, NY and Cleveland, OH (Box 11)
  - American Education Lobby (Box 11)
  - American Emergency Committee on the Panama Canal (Box 11)
  - American Enterprise Association, Washington, DC (Box 11)
    [See also the American Enterprise Institute for Public Policy Research.]
  - American Enterprise Institute for Public Policy Research Financial, Washington, DC (Box 11)
    [Formerly called the American Enterprise Association See also American Enterprise Association and the Group Research directory under American Enterprise Institute for Public Policy Research.]
  - American Enterprise Institute for Public Policy Research, Washington, DC, 1986- (Box 11)
    [Formerly called the American Enterprise Association]
  - American Enterprise Institute for Public Policy Research, Washington, DC, 1980- (Box 12)
  - American Enterprise Institute for Public Policy Research General, Washington, DC, 1976- (Box 12)
  - American Enterprise Institute for Public Policy Research General, Washington, DC, 1972-75 (Box 12)
  - American Enterprise Institute for Public Policy Research General, Washington, DC (Box 13)
  - American Enterprise Institute for Public Policy Research Publications, Washington, DC (Box 13)
  - American Eugenics Party (Box 13)
  - American Family Institute, The (Box 13)
  - American Federation of Labor -- Congress of Industrial Organizations (AFL-CIO) News (Box 346)
    [See also the Group Research directory under Special Reports -- Voting Records and Indexes.]
  - American Federation of Physicians and Dentists (Box 13)
  - American Flag Committee (Box 13)
  - American Freedom Center (Box 13)
    [See also Freedoms Foundation and the Group Research directory under Special Reports -- Freedoms Foundation at Valley Forge (PA).]
  - American Freedom Network (Box 13)
  - American Freedom Rallies (Box 13)
    [See also National Indignation Convention.]
  - American Friends of Katanga (Box 13)
  - American Friends of the Middle East (Box 13)
  - American Friends of Vietnam (Box 13)
  - American Good Government Society Financial, Washington, DC (Box 13)
    [See also the Group Research directory under American Good Government Society and under Committee on Electoral College Reform (a subgroup of the American Good Government Society).]
  - American Good Government Society General, Washington, DC (Box 13)
  - American Good Government Society Newspaper, magazine, and "Congressional Record" clippings, Washington, DC (Box 13)
  - American Heritage Foundation (Box 13)
  - American Independent Party (Box 14)
  - American Industrial Health Council (Box 14)
  - American Institute for Economic Research (Box 14)
  - American Institute for Free Labor Development (Box 14)
  - American Institute for Public Service (Box 14)
  - American Institute of Governmental Research, Inc. (Box 14)
  - American Institute of Political Communication (Box 14)
  - American Institute of Political Research, Inc. (Box 14)
  - American Italian Anti-Defamation League (Box 14)
  - American Jewish Association (Box 14)
  - American Jewish Committee (Box 14)
  - American Jewish Forum (Box 14)
  - American Jewish League Against Communism, Inc. (Box 14)
  - American Labor (Box 14)
  - American Labor Conferences on International Affairs (Box 14)
  - American League of Lobbyists (Box 14)
  - American Legal Foundation (Box 14)
  - American Legion Newspaper clippings (Box 15)
  - American Legion Letters, resolutions, and general (Box 15)
  - American Legion "Congressional Record" clippings (Box 15)
  - American Legion Publications (Box 15)
  - American Liberty Crusader (Box 15)
  - American Lobby, The (Box 15)
  - American Legislative Exchange Council (Box 16)
  - American Legislative Exchange Council, 1986- (Box 16)
  - American Legislative Exchange Council (Box 16)
  - American Lobby (Box 16)
  - American Lobby (Box 16)
  - American Medical Association (AMA) "Congressional Record" clippings (Box 16)
  - American Medical Association (AMA) Clippings, 1969-71 (Box 16)
  - American Medical Association (AMA) Clippings, 1967-8 (Box 16)
  - American Medical Association (AMA) Clippings, 1966 (Box 16)
  - American Medical Association (AMA) Clippings, 1965 (Box 16)
  - American Medical Association (AMA) Clippings, 1964 (Box 16)
  - American Medical Association (AMA) Clippings, 1961-3 (Box 16)
  - American Medical Association (AMA) Clippings, 1953-60 (Box 16)
  - American Medical Association (AMA) Clippings, -1953 (Box 16)
  - American Medical Association (AMA) General (Box 16)
  - American Medical Association (AMA) Magazine articles on (Box 17)
  - American Medical Association (AMA) Medicare (Box 17)
  - American Medical Association (AMA) AMPAC (Box 17)
  - American Medical Association (AMA) Rural Health (Box 17)
  - American Mercury (Box 17)
  - American Military Party (Box 17)
  - American Nazi Party Publications (Box 18)
  - American Nazi Party General (Box 18)
  - American Nazi Party Magazine and "Congressional Record" clippings (Box 18)
  - American Nazi Party Newspaper clippings, 1980- (Box 18)
  - American Nazi Party Newspaper clippings, 1971- (Box 18)
  - American Nazi Party Newspaper clippings (Box 19)
  - "American Opinion", Belmont, MA (Box 19)
    [Started by Robert Welch, Founder of the John Birch Society See also the John Birch Society and the Group Research directory under "American Opinion."]
  - American Opinion Bookstores (Box 19)
  - American Opinion Forum (Box 19)
  - American Opinion Library National and local (Box 19)
  - American Opinion Speakers Bureau Speech in a Social Movement 1967 (MA thesis), Brookfield, MA (Box 19)
    [Founded by the John Birch Society See also the Group Research directory under American Opinion Speakers Bureau.]
  - American Opinion Speakers Bureau, Brookfield, MA (Box 20)
  - American Ordinance Association (Box 20)
  - American Orthodox Church of North America (Box 20)
  - American Party General (Box 20)
  - American Party, AR (Box 20)
  - American Party, CA (Box 20)
  - American Party, Washington DC (Box 20)
  - American Party, FL (Box 20)
  - American Party, Savannah, GA (Box 20)
  - American Party, ID (Box 20)
  - American Party, IL (Box 20)
  - American Party, IN (Box 20)
  - American Party, IA (Box 20)
  - American Party, KS (Box 20)
  - American Party, MD (Box 20)
  - American Party, MA (Box 20)
  - American Party, MI (Box 20)
  - American Party, MO (Box 20)
  - American Party, NJ (Box 20)
  - American Party, OH (Box 20)
  - American Party, OK (Box 20)
  - American Independent Party, TX (Box 20)
  - American Party, UT (Box 20)
  - American Party, VA (Box 20)
  - American Party, WI (Box 20)
  - American Party (and Foundation), The (Box 20)
  - American Patriot Hall of Fame (Box 20)
  - American Patriots (Box 20)
  - American Patriots (Box 20)
  - American Peace Society (Box 20)
  - "American People" (Box 20)
    [Publication of National Association for the Advancement of White People (NAAWP) See also National Association for the Advancement of White People (NAAWP).]
  - American Political Science Association (Box 20)
  - American Politics (Box 20)
  - American Progress Foundation, Los Angeles, CA (Box 21)
    [See also the Organization for Repeal of Federal Income Taxes, Dallas B. Lewis, Willis E. Stone, and the National Committee for Economic Freedom as well as the Group Research directory under American Progress Foundation.]
  - American Protestant Defense League (Box 21)
  - American Public Relations Forum, Inc. (Box 21)
  - American Publications (Box 21)
  - American Purpose (Box 21)
  - American Research Foundation (Box 21)
  - American Review, The (Box 21)
  - American Schools and Colleges Association (Box 21)
  - American Sentinel, 1993- (Box 21)
  - American Sentinel, The (Box 21)
  - American Society for the Defense of Tradition, Family and Property, The (Box 21)
  - American Society for Industrial Security (Box 21)
  - American Society of African Culture (Box 21)
  - American Society of Local Officials (Box 21)
  - American-Southern Africa Council (Box 21)
    [First of two folders.]
  - American-Southern Africa Council (Box 22)
    [Second of two folders.]
  - American Space Frontiers Committee (Box 22)
  - American Standard (Box 22)
  - American States' Rights Party (Box 22)
  - "American Statesman, The", Salt Lake City, UT (Box 22)
    [Publisher/editor, J. Bracken Lee See also J. Bracken Lee and the Group Research directory under "American Statesman, The."]
  - American Strategy, Inc. (Box 22)
  - American Studies Center, The (Box 22)
  - American Surveys (Box 22)
  - American Taxpayers' Association, Fall River, MA (Box 22)
  - American Teachers (Box 22)
  - American Themes (Box 22)
  - American Thought and Action (Box 22)
  - American Thrift Assembly (Box 22)
  - American Trucking Association (Box 22)
  - American-Ukranian Republican Council (Box 22)
  - American United, Malibu, CA (Box 22)
  - American United Council (Box 22)
  - American Veterans Committee (Box 22)
  - American View (Box 23)
  - American Viewpoint, Inc. (Box 23)
  - American Volunteer Group (Box 23)
  - American Voters Federation (Box 23)
  - American Way Feature, Inc. Los Angeles, CA (Box 23)
  - American Way, Inc., The, Evansville, IN (Box 23)
  - American Youth for a Just Peace (Box 23)
  - American Zionist Federation (Box 23)
  - Americana (Box 23)
  - Americanism Center (Box 23)
  - Americanism Educational League, Los Angeles, CA (Box 23)
    [See also the Group Research directory under Americanism Educational League and Americans for Cuban Freedom (a committee of the Americanism Educational League).]
  - Americanist Political Action (Box 23)
  - Americanist Research and Defense Fund (Box 23)
  - Americans Against Socialized Medicine (Box 23)
  - Americans Building Constitutionally, Barrington, IL (Box 23)
  - Americans for a Sound Foreign Policy (Box 23)
  - Americans for Agnew (Box 23)
  - Americans for America (Box 23)
  - Americans for Biblical Government (Box 23)
  - Americans for Bush (Box 23)
  - Americans for Congressional Action to Free the Baltic States (Box 23)
  - Americans for Conservative Action (Box 23)
  - Americans for Conservative Education (Box 23)
  - Americans for Constitutional Action (ACA) "Congressional Record" clippings, Washington, DC (Box 23)
    [See also the Group Research directory under Americans for Constitutional Action (ACA), under Charles A. McManus, Jr. (former Executive Director, Americans for Constitutional Action), under Special Reports -- Voting Records and Indexes, and under Special Reports -- Americans for Constitutional Action (ACA).]
  - Americans for Constitutional Action Articles on (newsletter, magazine, speeches, and general reports) (Box 24)
  - Americans for Constitutional Action Financial Information (Box 24)
  - Americans for Constitutional Action General, 1971- (Box 24)
  - Americans for Constitutional Action General (Box 24)
  - Americans for Constitutional Action, 1976- (Box 25)
  - Americans for Constitutional Action News releases (Box 25)
  - Americans for Constitutional Action Newspaper clippings, 1971- (Box 25)
  - Americans for Constitutional Action Newspaper clippings (Box 25)
  - Americans for Effective Law Enforcement (Box 25)
  - Americans for Freedom (Box 25)
  - Americans for Law and Order (Box 25)
  - Americans for Liberty and Independence (Box 25)
  - Americans for National Security (AFNS), Washington, DC (Box 25)
    [See also the Group Research directory under Americans for National Security (AFNS).]
  - Americans for Nuclear Energy (Box 25)
  - Americans for Patriotism (Box 25)
  - Americans for Peace (Box 26)
  - Americans for the Competitive Enterprise System (Box 26)
  - Americans for the National Voter Initiative Amendment (Box 26)
  - Americans for Political Responsibility (Box 26)
  - Americans for the Preservation of the White Race (Box 26)
  - Americans for the Reagan Agenda (Box 26)
  - Americans (of Lebanese-Syrian Ancestry) for America (Box 26)
  - Americans on Guard (Box 26)
  - Americans United (Box 26)
  - Americans United for Life (Box 26)
  - America's Future, Inc. Operation Textbook, New Rochelle, NY (Box 26)
    [See also the Group Research Directory under Textbook Evaluation Committee and America's Future.]
  - America's Future, Inc. Financial, New Rochelle, NY (Box 26)
  - America's Future, Inc. General, New Rochelle, NY, 1982- (Box 26)
  - America's Future, Inc. General, New Rochelle, NY, 1973- (Box 27)
  - America's Future, Inc. General, New Rochelle, NY (Box 27)
  - America's Victory Force (Box 27)
  - Americus Foundation (Box 27)
  - Ammunition (Box 27)
  - Amnesty International (Box 27)
  - Amvets (Box 27)
  - Amway (Box 27)
  - Amway Sales (Box 28)
  - Know Your Enemy Amyx, Hurst (Box 28)
  - "Analysis" (Box 28)
  - Anderson, E. L. (Ph.D.) (Box 28)
  - Anderson, John B. R-IL (Box 28)
  - Anderson, Martin (Box 28)
  - Anderson, Robert O. (Box 28)
  - Anderson, Tom Magazine and "Congressional Record" clippings, Nashville, TN (Box 28)
    [See also the Group Research directory under Tom Anderson.]
  - Anderson, Tom Newspaper clippings (Box 28)
  - Anderson, Tom Columns (Box 28)
  - Anderson, Tom General (Box 28)
  - Anderson, William R. (Capt.) (Box 29)
  - Anderson, Mark (Box 29)
  - Andrews, T. Coleman, Richmond, VA (Box 29)
    [See also the Group Research directory under T. Coleman Andrews.]
  - Anglo-Saxon Christian Crusade, Inc. (Box 29)
  - Annenberg, Walter (Box 29)
  - Annis, Edward R. (Dr.) (Box 29)
  - Answers (Box 29)
  - Anti-Communism -- General (Box 29)
  - Anti-Bolshevik Bloc of Nations (Box 29)
  - Anti-Anti-Communism (Box 29)
  - Anti-Communist Advisory Committee Material related to Edward Hunter's allegation of a Moscow-directed effort to undermine domestic U.S. anti-communist efforts (Box 29)
  - Anti-Communist Advisory Committee (Box 29)
  - Anti-Communist Book Club, The (Box 29)
  - Anti-Communist Christian Association (Box 29)
  - Anti-Communist League (Box 29)
  - Anti-Communist League of the Americas (Box 29)
  - Anti-Communist Liaison, Arlington, VA (Box 29)
    [See also Edward Hunter and the Group Research directory under Anti-Communist Liaison.]
  - Anti-Communist Voters League (ACVL) Jackson, Donald (Rep., R-CA), Los Angeles, CA (Box 29)
    [See also the Group Research directory under Anti-Communist Voters League (ACVL).]
  - Anti-Defamation League of B'Nai B'Rith (Box 29)
  - Anti-Semitism, 1991- (Box 30)
  - Anti-Semitism, 1974- (Box 30)
  - Anti-Semitism (Box 30)
  - Anti-Subversive League, The (Box 30)
  - App, Austin J. (Dr.) (Box 30)
  - Appeal to Reason, The (Box 30)
  - "Appendix Nine" (Box 30)